<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Bradley D. Mattan, Ph.D.</title>
    <link>https://bmattan.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://bmattan.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021 19:33:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://bmattan.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://bmattan.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Receptivity to Health Messaging with fMRI</title>
      <link>https://bmattan.github.io/project/pa2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021 19:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bmattan.github.io/project/pa2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Differentiating the neural representations of self-relevance and valence is important because perceptions of message relevance and message valence may distinctively predict message effectiveness. In this study, I used a data-driven method to identify separate patterns of neural co-activation indexing judgments of self-relevance and valence and then explored how these patterns can be used to predict receptivity to health messaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using fMRI data from a localizer task that asks participants to judge the self-relevance and valence of trait adjectives, I conducted two separate partial least squares (PLS) analyses. Each PLS analysis contrasted either self-relevance or valence judgments with a letter case judgment control task. Despite high overall similarity between the resulting maps, r=.95, I identified a cortical midline pattern (VMPFC/PCC) that showed maximal divergence between the self-relevance and valence judgment patterns (see Figure). For each whole-brain and midline-masked map, I computed trial-wise dot product similarity to betaseries images reflecting neural responses to messages in a separate messaging task promoting physical activity in 158 sedentary adults. I then used these trial-wise similarity scores to predict message ratings and subsequently measured changes in everyday physical activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarity to either whole-brain PLS map (i.e., for self-relevance or valence) was associated with: (1) lower in-scan ratings of relevance of messages, and (2) less post-scan message agreement. In sum, similarity to whole-brain neural patterns tracking deliberation about the self-relevance or valence of information was associated with reduced message receptivity, suggesting possible counterarguing. Within the midline-masked images, I found that similarity to the masked valence judgment map was generally associated with lower message receptivity, as in the whole-brain similarity analyses. However, trial-wise similarity to the masked self-relevance judgment map was associated with increased message receptivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These findings suggest that increased coactivation between the VMPFC and PCC that arises during deliberate judgments of self-relevance may be part of a neural signature underlying message receptivity. Moving beyond a focus on mean activity in singular brain regions, these findings highlight potential predictive utility of commonalities and differences in the neural patterns of coactivation underlying judgments about self-relevance and valence. Specifically, coordinated neural activity within the VMPFC/PCC resembling patterns that arise during judgments about self-relevance (and not valence) are associated with increased receptivity to message-based interventions promoting real-world physical activity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 Projects</title>
      <link>https://bmattan.github.io/project/covid-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021 16:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bmattan.github.io/project/covid-19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the COVID-19 pandemic, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cn.asc.upenn.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Communication Neuroscience Lab&lt;/a&gt; has been actively studying what kind of messaging effectively encourages actions that benefit public health (e.g., wearing masks, avoiding large social gatherings) and greater compassion (e.g., checking in on and supporting vulnerable people). Working together with my fellow lab mates, I have been involved in three manuscripts that investigate how people respond to COVID-19 and pandemic-related health messaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;dispositional-victimhood&#34;&gt;Dispositional Victimhood&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dispositional victimhood (i.e., someone&amp;rsquo;s tendency to feel like a victim in general, not just in the pandemic) has been associated with lower empathy and greater sensitivity to threats. In one study with over 600 participants, we found that dispositional victimhood was associated with more positive responses to stories of people suffering during the pandemic. This greater positivity predicted less support for policies aimed at slowing the spread of the coronavirus and greater support for quickly reopening the economy. In a registered report (under review), we aim to replicate this finding, testing for specific mechanisms such as empathy and schadenfreude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;narrative-messaging&#34;&gt;Narrative Messaging&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Narrative messages are first-person accounts describing someone&amp;rsquo;s personal story. Narrative messages can reduce defensiveness and increase engagement with the message content through relatable protagonists. In this student-led project, we are examining how narrative messaging (vs. matter-of-fact expository messaging) can be used to increase concern for and actions favoring people who are especially vulnerable at this time (e.g., unemployed people, healthcare workers, prisoners). Participants in the narrative condition reported greater transportation into the message compared to participants in the expository condition. Consistent with our pre-registered predictions, we also observed indirect effects of narrative (vs. expository) messages, through increased message transportation, on: (1) beliefs that by physical distancing, one can protect vulnerable people, (2) beliefs that members of the target groups (i.e., healthcare workers and people who are incarcerated) were vulnerable, (3) intentions to engage in prosocial behaviors that help family and friends, and (4) intentions to engage in prosocial behaviors that help members of vulnerable groups. Together these results suggest that narratives can be used to motivate prosocial action during the COVID-19 pandemic to the extent that the narratives elicit transportation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;collectivism&#34;&gt;Collectivism&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this student-led project, we hypothesized that collectivism, a cultural variable characterizing the extent that individuals see themselves in relation to others, contributes to people’s willingness to adhere to public health guidance (e.g., mask wearing, social distancing). Consistent with preregistered predictions, across three studies (n=2864), including a U.S. nationally representative sample, people’s collectivist orientation was positively associated with intentions, positive beliefs, norm perceptions, and policy support for the preventive behaviors. In separate analyses at the country level (n=69 countries), more collectivist countries demonstrated lower growth rate in both COVID-19 confirmed cases and deaths. Together, these studies demonstrate the positive role of collectivism at the individual- and country-level in reducing COVID-19 transmission, and highlight the need to consider culture in public health policies and communications.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Status-Based Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://bmattan.github.io/project/status-based-evaluation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021 13:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bmattan.github.io/project/status-based-evaluation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Across various projects with my collaborators in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ifsnlab.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Impression Formation Social Neuroscience Lab&lt;/a&gt;, I have been actively studying how we perceive social status in others and how perceived status ultimately shapes the evaluations and decisions we make about others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;perceiving-status-in-others&#34;&gt;Perceiving Status in Others&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent empirical and theoretical work suggests that visible cues of status such as clothing may shape impressions differently than when status is learned through person knowledge (Mattan &amp;amp; Kubota, 2020; Mattan, Kubota, &amp;amp; Cloutier, 2017; Mattan, Wei, Cloutier, &amp;amp; Kubota, 2018). In a pair of ongoing studies, I will be examining how we differentiate socioeconomic status (SES) based on visible cues such as clothing and more abstract or knowledge-based cues. In another study, I will be examining the assumption based so far on correlational methods that the inferior parietal cortex is responsible for status differentiation. Using transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) and mouse tracking, I will test the causal role of this brain region in differentiating hierarchical rank based on person knowledge. In sum, my research highlights both the ways that status can be inferred and the potential neural mechanisms underlying our ability to track our own and others’ positions within a given social hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;status-based-evaluations&#34;&gt;Status-Based Evaluations&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main line of work in this project demonstrates that perceived status in conjunction with salient social categories (e.g., race) can elicit spontaneous effects in person evaluation. In a series of five experiments (Mattan, Kubota, Venezia, Li, &amp;amp; Cloutier, 2019), I found consistent implicit evaluative bias as a function of perceived SES (i.e., high SES more positive than low SES). These experiments nonetheless revealed some boundary conditions for this novel status priming effect. For example, we found that status priming tended to be larger for White than Black targets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In another study, I used fMRI to examine neural activity in 61 White participants as they formed impressions of Black and White targets (Mattan, Kubota, Dang, &amp;amp; Cloutier, 2018). Univariate analyses revealed that external motivation to respond without racial prejudice (EMS) may attenuate the positive value (e.g., decreased blood flow in the VMPFC, NAcc) and/or salience (e.g., decreased blood flow in the NAcc, amygdala) of high status in a mixed-race context. A separate multivariate analysis (behavioral partial least squares) revealed that EMS was associated with overall less coordination of brain activity (irrespective of target race and status) within networks previously implicated in affect regulation, introspection, and social cognition (Mattan, Kubota, Li, Dang, &amp;amp; Cloutier, 2018). These findings open the door to future studies examining the contributions of this network to difficulties experienced by high-EMS individuals when navigating interracial interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken together, my research on status-based evaluations indicates that race and status biases can spontaneously arise in implicit evaluations and neural responses, potentially compounding existing racial disparities. However, socioeconomic disparities extend beyond race. In my recent work, I have begun to examine the intersections of status with gender. Linking diverse strands of research from social psychology, evolutionary psychology, and social neuroscience, In a registered report (Mattan &amp;amp; Cloutier, 2020) I found that men show greater implicit pro-wealthy bias than do women in a large pre-existing online sample from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/atymr/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Attitudes, Identities, and Individual Differences Study&lt;/a&gt;. This work is complemented by an independent fMRI study showing that men show greater responses to high (vs. low) SES targets during impression formation in brain regions associated with positive evaluations such as the VMPFC and nucleus accumbens (Barth, Mattan, Dang, &amp;amp; Cloutier, 2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;perceived-status-and-decision-making&#34;&gt;Perceived Status and Decision Making&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extending my work into the domain of decision making, I examined the role of perceived financial status in evaluations of unfair financial offers (e.g., Justice Game: Mattan, Barth, Thompson, FeldmanHall, Cloutier, &amp;amp; Kubota, 2020). I found that participants tended to favor the party with presumed lower standing—-this was the case even among participants reporting above-average subjective SES. Finally, punitive responses were also more likely when the context emphasized the privileged SES of the allocator rather than the underprivileged SES of the recipient. In more recent work, I have been investigating trust decisions in the context of a series of one-off investment decisions. Here, I find that people prefer to invest more in high-status partners, regardless of whether status is ascribed through color-coding or inferred through clothing. In sum, my decision-making work provides evidence that social hierarchy has important consequences for how individuals intervene to (re)distribute resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;relevant-publications&#34;&gt;Relevant Publications&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-76847-z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Barth, D. M., &lt;strong&gt;Mattan, B. D.&lt;/strong&gt;, Dang, T. P., &amp;amp; Cloutier, J. (2020). Regional and network neural activity reflect men’s preference for greater socioeconomic status during impression formation. &lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports, 10&lt;/em&gt;, 20302.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0232369&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mattan, B. D.&lt;/strong&gt;, Barth, D. M., Thompson, A., FeldmanHall, O., Cloutier, J., &amp;amp; Kubota, J. T. (2020). Punishing the privileged: Selfish offers from high-status allocators elicit greater punishment from third-party arbitrators. &lt;em&gt;PLoS ONE, 15&lt;/em&gt;(5), e0232369.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1098/rsos.191232&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mattan, B. D.&lt;/strong&gt;, &amp;amp; Cloutier, J. (2020) Pro-rich implicit bias increases with greater control over resources in men but not women. &lt;em&gt;Royal Society Open Science, 7&lt;/em&gt;, 191232.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-019-0770-8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mattan, B. D.&lt;/strong&gt;, &amp;amp; Kubota, J. T. (2020). Status beyond what meets the eye. &lt;em&gt;Nature Human Behaviour, 4&lt;/em&gt;, 233–234.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1177/0146167219835230&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mattan, B. D.&lt;/strong&gt;, Kubota, J. T., Venezia, S. A., Li, T., &amp;amp; Cloutier, J. (2019). Implicit evaluative biases toward targets varying in race and socioeconomic status. &lt;em&gt;Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin, 45&lt;/em&gt;, 1512-1527.&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1523/ENEURO.0039-18.2018&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mattan, B. D.&lt;/strong&gt;, Kubota, J. T., Li, T., Dang, T. P., &amp;amp; Cloutier, J. (2018). Motivation modulates brain networks in response to faces varying in race and status: A multivariate approach. &lt;em&gt;eNeuro, 5&lt;/em&gt;(4), e0039-18.2018.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.copsyc.2018.04.010&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mattan, B. D.&lt;/strong&gt;, Wei, K., Cloutier, J., &amp;amp; Kubota, J. T. (2018). The social neuroscience of race- and status-based prejudice. &lt;em&gt;Current Opinion in Psychology, 24&lt;/em&gt;, 27–34.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1093/scan/nsx128&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mattan, B. D.&lt;/strong&gt;, Kubota, J. T., Dang, T. P., &amp;amp; Cloutier, J. (2018). External motivation to respond without prejudice differentially alters neural processing of race and social status. &lt;em&gt;Social Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience, 13&lt;/em&gt;, 22–31.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1177/17456916166778&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mattan, B. D.&lt;/strong&gt;, Kubota, J. T., &amp;amp; Cloutier, J. (2017). How social status shapes person perception and evaluation: A social neuroscience perspective.  &lt;em&gt;Perspectives on Psychological Science, 12&lt;/em&gt;, 468–507.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roll the Same</title>
      <link>https://bmattan.github.io/project/rts/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2020 16:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bmattan.github.io/project/rts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;mission-of-roll-the-same&#34;&gt;Mission of Roll the Same&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rollthesame.org/our-mission&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;mission of Roll the Same&lt;/a&gt; is to work towards making Brazilian Jiu Jitsu (BJJ) a safe, inclusive, and welcoming space. We want to harness the potential of BJJ to be a force for bringing people from all backgrounds together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To accomplish this mission, Roll the Same (RTS) works in education, advocacy, and community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Education:&lt;/strong&gt; To provide education, support and resources to drive positive change and make the sport inclusive and safe for all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advocacy:&lt;/strong&gt; To maintain a platform and a network committed to increasing access and inclusion in BJJ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community:&lt;/strong&gt; To empower individual practitioners to engage with issues of equality and diversity, regardless of rank or level of involvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-contributions&#34;&gt;My Contributions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a volunteer analyst for RTS, my primary responsibility has been the analysis of mixed-methods data (i.e., quantitative and qualitative data) that were collected as part of the RTS 2020 community climate survey. I then summarized these analyses in a comprehensive report on gender inclusion within BJJ. The full 25-page report is available on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rollthesame.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;RTS website&lt;/a&gt;, but I provide the executive summary here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on our survey of 579 BJJ practitioners, including 189 women, I found evidence of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gyms and cultures that undervalue women.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sexualization of women by men who are their teammates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No mechanisms of accountability when misconduct arises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sexism in online BJJ culture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from being the right thing to do, greater gender inclusion can improve the prestige, profits, and technical prowess of any gym. To create a more welcoming environment, gyms can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be proactive in efforts to teach men how to be good training partners for women.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build general trust in instructors and amongst teammates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Establish and enforce a system that allows women to report sexual harassment/assult without negative consequences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;future-directions&#34;&gt;Future Directions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Complementing this report on gender inclusion, RTS also has data that shed light on the inclusion of racial and sexual minorities in BJJ. These data show that problems extend beyond gender inclusion to other minoritized groups. I plan to conduct analyses of these data, leading to the release of future reports on the state of inclusion in BJJ with regards to race and sexuality. Although I was not part of the RTS team when the 2020 community climate survey was conducted, I already have plans for future study proposals that focus on more targeted questions pertaining to social hierarchy within martial arts and its relationship to well-being and inclusion. I welcome inquiries from people interested in collaborating on this exciting project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GeoScan Smoking Study</title>
      <link>https://bmattan.github.io/project/geoscan/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2020 18:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bmattan.github.io/project/geoscan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;geoscan-project&#34;&gt;GeoScan Project&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an R01-funded project within the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cn.asc.upenn.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Communication Neuroscience Lab&lt;/a&gt;, GeoScan uses an innovative set of methods to test whether repeated, real-world exposure to point-of-sale tobacco marketing (POSTM) affects smoking behavior, and whether this is mediated by heightened craving and neural responses to POSTM. This novel multi-method approach includes mobile-phone based geolocation tracking, ecological momentary assessment (EMA), and functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI). By adding the ecological validity of observational field methods to the mechanistic insight of neuroimaging, and causal inferences from an experimental design, GeoScan aims to significantly advance actionable insight about POSTM effects in cancer control. Analyses will examine the extent to which POSTM increases brain responses to smoking cues as well as subjective craving, leading to increased smoking behavior&amp;ndash;a leading cause of cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;health-inequities-proposal&#34;&gt;Health Inequities Proposal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While helping to manage the GeoScan project, I have been working with pilot data to develop a grant proposal that examines the impact of poverty exposure on the links between momentary experiences of stress, cigarette cravings, and smoking. This proposal is motivated by existing work on the status-health gradient, which refers to the tendency for increasing social status to be associated with increasing health and well-being. Because much of the existing literature on the status-health gradient approaches this question at the society level (e.g., large surveys and public archives), it can be difficult to pinpoint the psychological mechanisms linking social status and actual health behaviors like smoking. Fortunately, the multi-modal approach of the GeoScan project affords several opportunities to examine the immediate psychological effects of poverty exposure on smoking, which is a leading cause of cancer. Concretely, I propose to study the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1) Does increasing exposure to poverty (defined by the average percentage of households below poverty at one’s current location within a ~4-hour time period) increase the positive association between stress (negative mood) and cigarette cravings?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(2) Does increasing exposure to poverty increase the positive relationship between cigarette cravings and smoking frequency (i.e., cigarettes smoked per hour)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(3) Is the indirect effect of stress on smoking through increased cigarette cravings stronger when participants find themselves within high-poverty areas?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
